Inventory of the Gino Charles Speranza papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Gino Charles Speranza papers
1904-1941
42012
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 24 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (24.4 linear feet)
The papers primarily document Gino Speranza's work as a journalist and foreign correspondent for Outlook and the New York Evening Post in Italy during the war and political and military attaché for the United States embassy in Rome from 1917 to 1919. The papers are comprised of writings, diaries, clippings, correspondence, reports, pamphlets, notes, photographs, and printed matter relating to Italian politics and diplomacy during World War I and in the postwar period. Also available on microfilm (34 reels).
Speranza, Florence Colgate, 1873-1951.
Speranza, Gino Charles, 1872-1927.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1942, with an increment in 1945
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (34 reels).
Related Materials
Gino Speranza Papers, New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division
Gino Speranza Papers, Italian American Collection, Immigration History Research Center, University of Minnesota
Comando di Fiume d'Italia. Bolletino ufficiale, Hoover Institution Archives
Luigi Aldrovandi Marescotti typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Moses Stephen Slaughter Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Benajah Harvey Carroll, Jr. Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, University of Texas at Austin
Thomas Nelson Page Papers, University of Virginia Library
Biographical/Historical Note
1872 April 23 Born, Bridgeport, Connecticut
1892 BS, City College of New York
1894 LLB, New York University Law School
1895 MS, City College of New York
1897 Legal counsel to Italian consulate general in New York City
1907-1905 Founding member, Society for the Protection of Italian Immigrants
1909 Marries Florence Colgate Speranza
1912 Gives up legal practice to pursue writing career and volunteer work
1915-1917 Featured correspondent for the New York Evening Post and Outlook, reporting on the war from the Italian front
1916 Chairman, Special Committee of the Committee for War Relief in Florence
1917 Member, General committee of American Relief Clearing House
1917 April Volunteered services to Ambassador Thomas Nelson Page in Rome and became a volunteer worker in the office of the U.S. military attaché
Circa 1919 Attaché on political intelligence, U.S. embassy in Rome
1925 Author, Race or Nation? A Conflict of Divided Loyalties
1927 July 12 Died
1941 Published (posthumously), The Diary of Gino Speranza: Italy 1915-1919, edited by Florence Colgate Speranza. New York: Columbia University
Source: George E. Pozzetta. "Speranza, Gino Carlo," http://www.anb.org/articles/15/15-01121.html; American National Biography Online Feb 2000. Accessed June 26, 2012.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers primarily document Gino Speranza's work as a journalist and war correspondent for Outlook and the New York Evening Post in Italy and political and military attaché for the United States embassy in Rome from 1917 to 1919, with materials relating to Italian politics and diplomacy during World War I and in the postwar period.
A highlight of the papers are Speranza's Diaries, which run from June 1915 to May 1919. His almost daily entries reflect on the news of each day, his interactions with Italian and American officials, stories of the Italian people during wartime, and his travels with his wife, Florence Colgate Speranza. The diaries from 1918 to 1919 include entries on the debate over Italian territorial claims and other issues discussed at the Paris Peace Conference. Letters, telegrams, photographs and postcards are interfiled with the diary pages.
In 1941, Speranza's diaries were edited and published in two volumes by Florence Colgate Speranza, who also volunteered for various war relief agencies in Italy during the war. In preparation for this publication, Florence Colgate compiled seventeen Scrapbooks containing photographs, clippings, letters, printed matter, and ephemera that correspond to the pages of the published diaries. Some notes on the photographs and correspondence are in Speranza's handwriting however clippings and postcards dated after 1927 confirm that the scrapbooks were compiled after his death. Florence Colgate's own personal diary is in the Florence Colgate Speranza file.
As a journalist embedded with Italian soldiers along the Isonzo river and in the Alps, Speranza's Writings are comprised mainly of his firsthand reports from the frontline. Some topics he addresses include America's role in the war, the Adriatic question, the effects of war on Italian towns on the front, and the difficulties of fighting at high altitudes. Many of these experiences are also recollected in his Diaries. The series also contains some articles written after the war as well as Speranza's writings and reports from his time as an attaché to the American embassy in Rome.
In the Correspondence series are the letters Speranza received from an Italian American soldier stationed in Bari named Esterino Alex Tarasca. Speranza's interactions with Tarasca inspired a series of short stories titled "American I.," a draft of which is included in his Writings. Other correspondence of note includes letters exchanged with U.S. ambassador to Italy Thomas Nelson Page and American consul to Italy B. Harvey Carroll, Jr.
The container list for the papers includes a numbering system taken from envelopes that originally housed the collection materials. The numbers refer to a preliminary inventory of the papers most likely created when they arrived at the archives in 1942. Although the numbers do not appear to have any logical sequence, they identify materials that were originally grouped together and for this reason, when available, the numbers were carried over onto the folder titles. For example, II-34 indicates Section II, Envelope 34. While this numbering system has been retained, similar materials have been combined in series to facilitate research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in ten series: Biographical file, Diaries, Correspondence, Writings, Italy subject file, Clippings, Photographs and postcards, Florence Colgate Speranza, Scrapbooks, and Oversize materials
D'Annunzio, Gabriele, 1863-1938.; Italy--Civilization.; Italy--Description and travel.; Italy--Foreign relations--United States.; Italy--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Italy--History--1914-1945.; Italy--Politics and government--1914-1945.; Italy--Social conditions.; Military attachés.; Rijeka (Croatia)--History.; United States--Foreign relations--Italy.; World War, 1914-1918--Italy.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Italy.
- Biographical file, 1915-1918 (Box 1:)
  Scope and Contents note
  Article, letters of introduction, and safe conduct papers.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Article about Speranza published in La Vita Italiana, 1919 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Letters of introduction and press credentials, 1915-1918 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Safe conduct papers, 1916 April-June (Folder 1: 3)
    Copies
- Diaries, 1915-1919 (Box 3-8:)
  Includes holograph diaries (in English) containing correspondence, postcards, photographs, stamps, clippings, menus, flyers, programs, and dried flowers, from Speranza's years in Italy during the war.
  Arranged in numerical order by volume number
  - "Italian Diary. European War, 1915-1916" (Folder 3-6:)
    - Volume I, 1915 August 12-October 21 (Folder 3:)
    - Volume II, 1915 October 25-1916 January 4 (Folder 3:)
    - Volume III, 1916 January 5-April 21 (Folder 4:)
    - Volume IV, 1916 April 23-May 24 (Folder 4:)
    - Volume V, 1916 June-July 2 (Folder 5:)
    - Volume VI, 1916 July 3-July 29 (Folder 5:)
    - Volume VII, 1916 August 1-October 9 (Folder 5:)
    - Volume VIII, 1915 June-1917 December (Folder 6:)
      Contains no diary entries. Scrapbook of postcards, stamps, photographs, telegrams, correspondence, and identification documents
    - Volume IX, 1916 October 17-1917 June 2 (Folder 6:)
  - "Italian Diary. European War, 1917-1918" (Folder 7:)
    - Volume X, 1917 July 19-1918 March 28 (Folder 7:)
  - Italian Diary. European War, 1918" (Folder 7-8:)
    - Volume XI, 1918 April 6-October 20 (Folder 7:)
    - Volume XII, 1918 November 28-December 17 (Folder 8:)
  - "Italian Diary. European War, 1919" (Folder 8:)
    - Volume XIII, 1919 March 25-April 7 (Folder 8:)
- Correspondence, 1914-1919 (Box 1-2:)
  Contains letters and enclosures, in English and Italian, collected and written during the course of Speranza's time as a war correspondent and political attaché to the American embassy in Rome. Includes some typescript copies (originals in diary or New York Public Library).
  Arranged in two groups: General correspondence (I-35 and I-36) and Attaché to U.S. embassy in Rome correspondence (IV-8 and IV-9), then alphabetically
  - General correspondence (I-35 and I-36) (Folder 1-2:)
    - Unidentified, 1917-1919 (Folder 1: 4)
    - A-D, 1914-1919 (Folder 1: 5)
    - D'Adamo, Agostino, 1915-1918 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Aldrovandi Marescotti, Luigi, 1915-1916 (Folder 1: 7)
    - American Committee for War Relief in Florence, 1919 (Folder 1: 8)
    - American Free Milk and Relief for Italy (Mrs. John Drake), 1919 (Folder 1: 9)
    - American Red Cross in Rome, (James Byrne, Joseph Collins, Major Aldrich, William R. Hereford, Paul Kellogg, L. Witmer), 1917-1919 (Folder 1: 10)
    - American Relief Clearing House (John Gray), 1917 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Anderson, T. Hart, 1918-1919 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Apollonio, Ferdinando, 1916-1919 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Ashburner, Walter, 1916-1918 (Folder 1: 14)
      Includes one letter from Speranza to Angiolo Orvieto ( Il Marzocco) regarding Ashburner
    - Associazione Politica Fra Gli Italiani Irredenti, 1918 (Folder 1: 15)
    - The Atlantic Monthly (Ellery Sedgwick), 1915-1918 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Barbarich, E., 1916-1917 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Branchi, Giovanni, 1918-1919 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Buckey, M. C., 1917-1918 (Folder 1: 19)
    - Butterfield, Kenyon L., 1919 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Carroll, B. Harvey, Jr., 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 21)
    - Carroll, Daisy (Mrs. B. Harvey), 1916-1919 (Folder 1: 22)
    - DeCicco, Pasquale L., 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Colasanti, Arduino, 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 24)
    - Colgate, Lathrop, Mrs., 1916 (Folder 1: 25)
    - Comitato Nazionale Polacco Missione in Italia, 1918 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Downes, John H., 1918 (Folder 1: 27)
      Regarding Orphans Committee at Amalfi
    - Dunham, Carroll, 1916-1919 (Folder 1: 28)
    - E-J, 1916-1919 (Folder 1: 29)
    - Enriques, Federigo, 1919 (Folder 1: 30)
    - Ferrando, Emilio, 1919 (Folder 1: 31)
    - Foa, Rudolfo, 1918 (Folder 1: 32)
    - de Forest, Robert W., 1915-1917 (Folder 1: 33)
    - Freeman, Lewis R., 1916-1918 (Folder 1: 34)
    - Galante, Andrea, 1917 (Folder 1: 35)
    - Gay, H. Nelson, 1918 (Folder 1: 36)
    - Ginelli, Giuseppe, 1915-1918 (Folder 1: 37)
    - Howe, Henry M., 1915-1919 (Folder 1: 38)
    - Howland, Harold, 1918 (Folder 1: 39)
    - K-P, 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 1)
    - LaGorce, John Oliver, 1917 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Lathrop, Stanley, 1916-1918 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Léon, Maurice, 1916 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Loret, Mattia, 1918 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Lowrie, Walter, 1916 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Marangoni, Luigi, 1916-1918 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Mayor des Planches, Edmondo, 1919 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Mazzoni, M., Colonello, 1917 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Minozzi, Giovanni, 1917 (Folder 2: 10)
    - The New Republic (Herbert Croly and Walter Weyl), 1915-1916 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Nitti, Francesco Saverio, 1918 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Nollen, J. S., 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Novelli, Augusto, undated (Folder 2: 14)
    - Official Committee on Public Information in the United States (John Hearley, Charles E. Merriam, J. Kingsley Moses), 1918 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Ojetti, Ugo, 1915-1916 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Outlook (Ernest H. and Lawrence F. Abbott), 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Page, Florence L. (Mrs. Thomas Nelson), 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Platt, Charles A., 1918 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Porro, Francesco, 1918 (Folder 2: 21)
    - R-W, 1914-1919 (Folder 2: 22)
    - Richardon, Norval, 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 23)
    - Ryerson, N. C., 1915-1916 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Shotwell, J. T., 1919 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Simoni, Renato, 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Siretti, Edoardo, 1916 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Symonds, C. J., 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 28)
    - Tarasca, Esterino Alex, 1915-1919 (Folder 2: 29)
    - Weillschott, Gustavo, 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 30)
    - General miscellaneous, 1918 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Attaché to the U.S. embassy in Rome correspondence (IV-8 and IV-9) (Folder 2:)
    - General. Telegrams, sent and received, 1917-1919 (Folder 2: 32)
    - Unidentified, 1917-1919 (Folder 2: 33)
    - Buckey, M. C., 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 34)
    - Carroll, B. Harvey, Jr., 1918 (Folder 2: 35)
    - Gibson, Hugh, 1918 (Folder 2: 36)
    - Jay, Peter A., 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 37)
    - Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 38)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, 1918-1919 (Folder 2: 39)
    - Post, Chandler R., 1918 (Folder 2: 40)
    - Prato, Carlo E., 1918 (Folder 2: 41)
    - Richardson, Norval, 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 42)
- Writings, 1916-1929 (Box 9-11:)
  Contains typescript, holograph, and printed copies of articles, short stories, and poems, mostly written from the Italian front
  Arranged in groups chronologically
  - Undated drafts (I-5) (Folder 9:)
    - "Italian Immigration and the War," draft, undated (Folder 9: 1)
    - "Characteristics of the Italian Soldier," draft, undated (Folder 9: 2)
  - Typescript copies of published and unpublished articles written during the war, from Italy, 1914-1919. (II-2) (Folder 9:)
    - Undated
      - "All Against One-One Against All" (Folder 9: 3)
      - "American I." (Folder 9: 4)
        Draft
      - "A Glacier Battle on the Italian Front" (Folder 9: 5)
      - "How Italy Rests Her Soldiers From the Trenches" (Folder 9: 6)
      - "The Interest in Art of a Nation at War" (Folder 9: 7)
      - "The Irredenti" (Folder 9: 8)
      - "Italia!" (Folder 9: 9)
      - "The Italo-Serbo-Albanian Entente Cordiale" (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Italy and the Montenegrin Mystery" (Folder 9: 11)
      - "Martyrs, Past and Present, of Italian Nationalism" (Folder 9: 12)
      - "Opinions and Tendencies in Italy in Regard to the New Developments of the European Conflict" (Folder 9: 13)
      - "La Posta (The Lieutenant's Story)." (Folder 9: 14)
        Short story regarding repair of teleferica by Alpino lieutenant
      - "The Question of the Italo-Austrian Frontier (Why Italy Is Fighting for a New Boundary-; Why in 1866 She Was Obliged to Accept the Present Indefensible Confines)" (Folder 9: 15)
      - "Roma Vincitrix" (Folder 9: 16)
      - "Roman Days" (Folder 9: 17)
      - "La Serenissima." (Folder 9: 18)
        Regarding air raid on Venice, October 1915
      - "The Tragic Instant (Padre Serafino's Story." (Folder 9: 19)
      - "The War in the Dolomites" (Folder 9: 20)
      - "Young Glory!" (Folder 9: 21)
    - 1914 (Folder 9: 22)
    - 1915 (Folder 9: 23)
    - 1916 (Folder 9: 24-25)
    - 1917 (Folder 9: 26)
    - 1918 (Folder 9: 27)
    - 1919 (Folder 9: 28)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 1915 May 30 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Field notes from the war front, 1916-1917. (I-34) (Folder 10: 2)
    Includes 9 booklets
  - Notebooks and notes containing holographic drafts of articles, 1916-1918. (IV-15) (Folder 10: 3)
  - Scrapbook of articles published in the New York Evening Post and The Outlook, 1916-1920. (I-2) (Folder 10: 4)
  - Printed copies of published articles, 1916-1926. (I-17 and I-23) (Folder 10:)
    - "An Italian on America," The Independent, undated (Folder 10: 5)
    - "Some Aspects of the Struggle," The Nation, 1916 February (Folder 10: 6)
    - "Italy's Decadence and Italy's Mission," The Nation, 1919 (Folder 10: 7)
    - "Does Americanization Americanize?" The Atlantic Monthly, 1920 February (Folder 10: 8)
    - "Italy's Crisis Subsiding," Current History, 1921 March (Folder 10: 9)
    - "The Newest Freedom," The Hubbert Journal, 1921 April (Folder 10: 10)
    - "Italian Contrasts," The Yale Review, 1921 April (Folder 10: 11)
    - "Deeper Misgivings," The Atlantic Monthly, 1922 June (Folder 10: 12)
    - "Bissolati--And the Revolt of Italy's Youth," Our World, 1923 (Folder 10: 13)
    - "The Religion of American Diplomacy," Forum, 1928 January (Folder 10: 14)
    - "The Citizenship of the Pope," Our World, 1923 (Folder 10: 15)
    - "A Diplomatic Incident: When Washington Closed Out Vatican Ministry," The Atlantic Monthly, 1929 October (Folder 10: 16)
  - Writings and reports from work with U.S. embassy in Rome relating to political events, 1918. (IV-19) (Folder 10: 17)
  - Typescript copies of published and unpublished articles written after the war, from New York and Vermont, 1919-1921. (I-9) (Folder 10: 18)
  - English translation of an article by Benito Mussolini published in Gerarchia, circa 1923 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes and research materials, 1916-1918 (Folder 11: 2)
- Italy subject file, 1904-1926 (Box 11-15:)
  Includes clippings, brochures, bulletins, pamphlets, monographs, leaflets, writings, and notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - After the war problems, 1916-1918. (II-3.35) (Folder 11: 3)
  - Albania, undated (Folder 11: 4)
  - America and emigration, 1915-1918. (II-3.18) (Folder 11: 5)
  - America and the War, 1917-1919. (II-3.31) (Folder 11: 6)
  - American Committee on Public Information, 1917-1919. (IV-27) (Folder 11: 7)
  - American Relief Clearing House in Rome, 1917. (I-5) (Folder 11: 8)
  - Armistices, Battle of Novara, undated (Folder 11: 9)
  - Art and music programs, 1915-1918. (V-17) (Folder 11: 10)
  - Art and the War (Reconstruction), 1915-1919. (II-3.20) (Folder 11: 11-12)
  - Art industries during WWI, 1917-1918. (I-2) (Folder 11: 13)
  - Austrian prisoners and refugees, 1915. (I-1) (Folder 11: 14)
  - Belgian relief, circa 1914. (I-6) (Folder 11: 15)
  - Biographies, 1916-1919. (II-3.23) (Folder 11: 16-17)
  - Bombarded cities, 1915-1917. (II-3.24) (Folder 11: 18)
  - Cadorna, Luigi. Comando Supremo announcements, 1916. (IV-7) (Folder 12: 1)
    See also Oversize materials
  - Camera dei Deputati. Transcripts from public hearings, 1916 March. (IV-24) (Folder 12: 2)
  - Carroll, B. Harvey, caricature, 1918 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Cavallini, Filippo, 1918. (IV-23) (Folder 12: 4)
  - Cavell, Edith execution, 1915 (Folder 12: 5)
  - Comitato d'Azione per il Trentino, 1915 (Folder 12: 6)
  - Commerce, 1915. (IV-25) (Folder 12: 7)
  - Conférence Pour l'Accord Entre les Peuples Opprimés Par l'Autriche-Hongrie, 1918 April 9. (IV-22) (Folder 12: 8)
  - D'Annunzio, Gabriele (Folder 12:)
    - Clippings, undated (Folder 12: 9)
    - Comando di Fiume d'Italia. Bollettino Ufficiale, 1919-1920. (II-4) (Folder 12: 10)
    - Leaflets dropped over Vienna, 1918 August 9. (I-29) (Folder 12: 11)
  - Dalmatia and Italians in Spalato [Split], circa 1918. (I-12) (Folder 12: 12)
  - Deputies, parties, and other political, 1917-1919. (II-3.40) (Folder 12: 13-14)
  - Economic, 1912-1917. (II-3.2) (Folder 12: 15)
  - Efficiency, undated (Folder 12: 16)
  - Fascism, 1923-1925 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Financial, 1915-1918. (II-3.15) (Folder 12: 18-19)
  - Gorizia, undated (Folder 12: 20)
  - Industrial, 1918-1919. (II-3.3) (Folder 12: 21)
  - Italian army, 1917-1918. (II-3.5) (Folder 12: 22)
  - Italian colonies, 1915-1919. (II-3.38) (Folder 12: 23)
  - Italian front, 1915-1919. (II-3.13) (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - Italian history, 1917. (II-3.9) (Folder 13: 3)
  - Italian places, 1910-1916. (II-3.16) (Folder 13: 4)
  - Italian press and journalists, 1918. (II-3.37) (Folder 13: 5)
  - Italian soldiers, images of, 1917-1918. (I-4) (Folder 13: 6)
  - Italy in the Balkans and east, undated. (II-3.14) (Folder 13: 7)
  - Labor, 1916-1919. (II-3.34) (Folder 13: 8)
  - League of Nations and Paris Peace Conference, 1919. (II-3.42) (Folder 13: 9)
  - Literature and the War, 1918. (II-3.12) (Folder 13: 10)
  - Maps, 1916. (I-22) (Folder 13: 11)
  - Martyrs, 1916. (II-3.22) (Folder 13: 12)
  - Navy and submarines, merchant marines, 1915-1918. (II-3.30) (Folder 13: 13)
  - Pamphlets and monographs, 1914-1919. (I-20) (Folder 13:)
    - 1914. Un mese di guerra: Documenti ufficiali, diario di guerra, Lettere di soldati dal campo, istantanee di guerra; Farinelli, Arturo. Giusta guerra atroce demenza; Forzano, Giovacchino. La favola del lupo, dell'orso, delle faine, del mastino, ecc. ecc. (Folder 13: 14)
    - 1915. Italijansko skofovstvo in vojska; Cantalupo, Roberto. Il primo soldato d'Italia; Fedele, Pietro. Why Italy Is At War? (Folder 13: 15)
    - 1916. Book of standards for war correspondents issued by the Italian army press office; Lustig, A. La Preparazione e la difesa sanitaria dell'esercito; Marcicci, Alessandro. "Per il contadino del lazio; La Nostra patria" (Folder 13: 16)
    - 1919. Il Diritto di Fiume Italiana riconsacrato nell'universita di Roma; Dati che possono illustrare lo sforzo fatto dall'Italia nella recente guerra contro gli imperi centrali (Folder 13: 17)
  - Papacy and religion, 1918. (II-3.4) (Folder 13: 18-19)
  - Papal consistory, 1915 November-December. (I-3) (Folder 14: 1)
  - Partito Cattolico, 1916-1918. (II-3.41) (Folder 14: 2)
  - Philanthropies and propaganda, 1917-1918. (II-3.25) (Folder 14: 3)
    Includes two issues of Fuori i barbari!
  - Plots, stories and scenes of Italy at war, 1917. (II-3.7) (Folder 14: 4)
  - Political, 1917-1918. (II-3.28) (Folder 14: 5)
  - The Pope, the Vatican, and the Church, 1915. (I-21) (Folder 14: 6)
  - Popular songs and war songs, 1915-1916. (II-3.8) (Folder 14: 7-8)
  - Prayers. "The Last Prayer of a Garibaldino,", undated (Folder 14: 9)
  - Profughis [Refugees] and prisoners, undated. (II-3.10) (Folder 14: 10)
  - Redeemed provinces and cities, 1915-1919. (II-3.1) (Folder 14: 11)
  - Relief agencies. See Welfare--Italian and American (Folder 14:)
  - "Report on Unauthorized Activities of American Citizens,", undated. (IV-21) (Folder 14: 12)
  - Schools, universities, and children, 1914-1917. (II-3.6) (Folder 14: 13)
  - Socialism, 1918. (II-3.21) (Folder 14: 14-15)
    Includes copies of Avanti! newspaper
  - Soldier's calendar and notebook, 1916 (Folder 15: 1)
  - Spies, 1917-1918. (II-3.27) (Folder 15: 2)
  - Stamps, undated. (I-4) (Folder 15: 3)
  - Stationery, undated. (I-13) (Folder 15: 4)
  - Treaties, pacts, and government announcements, 1918. (II-3.39) (Folder 15: 5)
  - Venice, 1916-1918. (II-3.17) (Folder 15: 6)
  - Villa Modigliani, undated. (I-30) (Folder 15: 7)
  - War legislation including censorship, 1919. (II-3.19) (Folder 15: 8)
  - War loans, 1917 (Folder 15: 9)
  - Welfare--Italian and American, 1917-1918. (IV-20) (Folder 15: 10)
    Includes printed matter and other materials of the Red Cross and other relief agencies in Italy